<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <link>https://eldarrak.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 Eldar Rakhimberdiev</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Ancient timers in dynamic environments</title>
      <link>https://eldarrak.github.io/post/phd-positon-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2018 20:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eldarrak.github.io/post/phd-positon-2019/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Our world is constantly cycling, with seasons passing by, the day coming after the night, the moon turning around the Earth and driving tidal rhythms. All living organisms have to align their lives with these cycles. It has long been studied how the ancient time-keeping programs regulate animal physiological and behavioural cycles at annual, daily or tidal or lunar scales. In avian chronobiology, experiments by Ebo Gwinner and Viktor Dolnik have become a classic. Recently, our supervisory team and others have been breathing new life in studies of nature’s enigmatic rhythms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many birds are born with internal time-keepers that help them anticipate rhythmic changes in the environment, such as the coming of spring and autumn. Birds then prepare to migrate, to breed, and to moult, just in time for the change of seasons. However, in our times environments are changing rapidly. Therefore, we need a better understanding of  time-keeping programs. This PhD project seeks to dissect biological time-keeping and look at it from the ecological perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, novel technologies, state-of-the-art analytical methods and the tools for remote observation open up new opportunities to look at biological clocks at a different level and, importantly, to answer acute questions, such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How migratory birds change their routines to the diverse environmental cycling along the flyway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do they adjust when environmental cycles get disrupted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How the ability, the pace and the pathways of adjustment depend on species’ life history.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We offer a fascinating and flexible PhD project, with a focus on avian time-keeping, but also with &lt;strong&gt;several options that a student can shape according to  his/her interests&lt;/strong&gt;. It will consist of the following 3 work packages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analysis of already collected data on time-keeping in captive birds&lt;/strong&gt;. Using existing unique long-term data from captive waders and songbirds, the student will look at birds’ ability to shift from internal time-keeping program to the rhythmic environment. We will examine whether the birds’ shifts depend on life-cycle stage.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analysis of data on behavioural routines of individuals from wearable trackers&lt;/strong&gt;. Using GPS and accelerometry data from free-flying birds of various species, the student will study the birds’ time-keeping in the wild and detect changes in their synchronization with their environments. With our help, the PhD student will (1) reveal behavioural cycles using  machine learning to classify behaviour from accelerometery data and (2) match the behavioural cycles with animals’ locations from GPS data and with environmental cycles from numerical model predictions and/or Earth Observation datasets.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experimental work in captivity&lt;/strong&gt;. Using captive facilities, in Groningen and possibly also in Russia, the student will be able to learn about, and carry out, studies of seasonal biology.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also scope for more in-depth quantitative approaches, for example modelling of annual-cycle activities or effects of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PhD project will take 4 years, of which 3 will be spent in Russia with interspersed visits to the Netherlands. The final year, and the initial PhD defence, will take place in the Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project will be supervised by Eldar Rakhimberdiev (Moscow State University), Julia Karagicheva (Royal Netherlands Institute for Sea Research) and Barbara Helm (University of Groningen).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interested? Please &lt;strong&gt;contact Eldar Rakhimberdiev&lt;/strong&gt; eldarrak@gmail.com&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Akesson, S., M. Ilieva, J. Karagicheva, E. Rakhimberdiev, B. Tomotani and B. Helm (2017). &amp;ldquo;Timing avian long-distance migration: from internal clock mechanisms to global flights.&amp;rdquo; Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences 372(1734).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Berger, A., K-M. Scheibe, S. Michaelis, and W. J. Streich. &amp;ldquo;Evaluation of living conditions of free-ranging animals by automated chronobiological analysis of behavior.&amp;rdquo; Behavior Research Methods, Instruments, &amp;amp; Computers 35, no. 3 (2003): 458-466.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Helm, B., R. Ben-Shlomo, M. J. Sheriff, R. A. Hut, R. Foster, B. M. Barnes and D. Dominoni (2013). &amp;ldquo;Annual rhythms that underlie phenology: biological time-keeping meets environmental change.&amp;rdquo; Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences 280(1765).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Karagicheva, J., E. Rakhimberdiev, A. Saveliev and T. Piersma (2018). &amp;ldquo;Annual chronotypes functionally link life histories and life cycles in birds.&amp;rdquo; Functional Ecology 32(10): 2369-2379.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plenary talk together with Theunis Piersma: Pinning down an ever moving target: establishing when and where migrant shorebird populations are bottlenecked</title>
      <link>https://eldarrak.github.io/talk/example-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eldarrak.github.io/talk/example-talk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flyway ecology: full annual cycle ecology of long-distance migrants</title>
      <link>https://eldarrak.github.io/project/population_ecology_of_long_distant_migrants/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eldarrak.github.io/project/population_ecology_of_long_distant_migrants/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;where-and-how-populations-of-seasonal-migrants-are-limited&#34;&gt;Where and how populations of seasonal migrants are limited?&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-parts-of-the-annual-cycle-are-interconnected&#34;&gt;How parts of the annual cycle are interconnected?&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-migrants-adjust-to-the-ongoing-changes&#34;&gt;How migrants adjust to the ongoing changes?&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To a great surprise we still have very limited answer to this questions. My current understanding is that there is not default limiting time or place and migratory populations respond to the selection pressures by adjusting their distributions in time and space. Together with Theunis Piersma, my teacher in Flyway Ecology, and his team we have already obtained some interesting results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ruffs&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Philomachus pugnax&lt;/em&gt;) shifted breeding grounds from Europe to Asia in response to changes on the migratory flyways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E. Rakhimberdiev&lt;/strong&gt;, Y. I. Verkuil, A. A. Saveliev, R. A. Väisänen, J. Karagicheva, M. Y. Soloviev, P. S. Tomkovich, and T. Piersma. A global population redistribution in a migrant shorebird detected with continent-wide qualitative breeding survey data. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Diversity and Distributions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, 17(1):  144–151, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y. I. Verkuil, N. Karlionova, &lt;strong&gt;E. Rakhimberdiev&lt;/strong&gt;, J. Jukema, J. J. Wijmenga, J. C. W, P. Pinchuk, E. Wymenga, A. J. Baker, and T. Piersma. Losing a staging area: Eastward redistribution of afro-eurasian ruffs is associated with deteriorating fuelling conditions along the western flyway. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Biological Conservation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, 149(1): 51–59, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Red knots&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Calidris canutus islandica&lt;/em&gt;) compensated strong decrease in survival at the wintering by increase of summer survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E. Rakhimberdiev&lt;/strong&gt;, P. J. van den Hout, M. Brugge, B. Spaans, and T. Piersma. Seasonal mortality and sequential density dependence in a migratory bird. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Avian Biology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, 46(4): 332–341, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another subspecies of &lt;strong&gt;red knot&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Calidris canutus canutus&lt;/em&gt;) seem to have trouble with fitting into the wintering ecological niche after growing in a warming Arctic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J. A. van Gils, S. Lisovski, T. Lok, W. Meissner, A. Ozarowska, J. de Fouw, &lt;strong&gt;E. Rakhimberdiev&lt;/strong&gt;, M. Y. Soloviev, T. Piersma, and M. Klaassen. Body shrinkage due to arctic warming reduces red knot fitness in tropical wintering range. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, 352(6287) :819–821, 2016.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://eldarrak.github.io/img/red_knot_science.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;red_knot_science&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contrary to them &lt;strong&gt;Bar-tailed godwits&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Limosa lapponica taymyrensis&lt;/em&gt;) can mitigate effects of climate warming in the Artic by increasing fuelling rates at the refuellign sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E. Rakhimberdiev&lt;/strong&gt;, S. Duijns, J. Karagicheva, C. J. Camphuysen, A. Dekinga, R. Dekker, A. Gavrilov, H. J. ten, J. Jukema, A. Saveliev, M. Soloviev, T. T. Lee, J. A. van Gils, and T. Piersma, Fuelling conditions at staging sites can mitigate arctic warming effects in a migratory bird. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nature communications&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, 9, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are just some first examples of our developments of Flyway Ecology. With the new data colllected globally by &lt;a href=&#34;https://teampiersma.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Theunis&amp;rsquo;s group&lt;/a&gt;, new biologging possibilites (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nioz.nl/en/waddenflyways&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://www.nioz.nl/en/waddenflyways&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://icarusinitiative.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;http://icarusinitiative.org&lt;/a&gt;), and new methods of statistical analysis allowing integration of variable datasets (my interest), we hope to get shortly to the new levels of understanding of ecolgy and evolution migrants and direct conservation efforts in much better ways.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FLightR: an R package for Solar Geolocation data Analysis</title>
      <link>https://eldarrak.github.io/project/solar_geolocation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eldarrak.github.io/project/solar_geolocation/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;While working at Cornell University with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eeb.cornell.edu/winkler/wordpress&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;David Winkler&lt;/a&gt; in 2011 I started development of a new technique for solar geolocation data analysis. Solar geolocators are the tiniest devices one can put on animals that record only light levels over time. In 2012 I joined a project &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nceas.ucsb.edu/featured/bridge&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Establishing an Open-source Animal-tracking Analysis Platform for Archival Geolocators&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; supported by the National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end I have developed R package &lt;strong&gt;FLightR&lt;/strong&gt;. I hope it will help researchers to get year round estimates of migratory animals&amp;rsquo; locations and behavioural states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how &lt;strong&gt;FLightR&lt;/strong&gt; works:
&lt;img src=&#34;https://eldarrak.github.io/img/geolocation_move_ecol.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;geolocation&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NB&lt;/strong&gt;: I cannot answer all FLightR and other geolocation related questions over email, concider &lt;a href=&#34;http://ornithologyexchange.org/forums/forum/259-geolocator-discussion-support/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ornithologyexchange&lt;/a&gt; and open issues for package problems at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/eldarrak/FLightR/issues&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;dedicated GitHub page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;publications&#34;&gt;Publications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E. Rakhimberdiev&lt;/strong&gt;, D. W. Winkler, E. Bridge, N. E. Seavy, D. Sheldon, T. Piersma, and A. Saveliev. A hidden markov model for reconstructing animal paths from solar geolocation loggers using templates for light intensity. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Movement Ecology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, 3(1), 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E. Rakhimberdiev&lt;/strong&gt;, N. Senner, M. Verhoeven, D. Winkler, W. Bouten, and T. Piersma. Comparing inferences of solar geolocation data against high-precision gps data: annual movements of a double-tagged black-tailed godwit. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Avian Biology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, 47(4): 589-596, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E. Rakhimberdiev&lt;/strong&gt;. Ornithology by light levels today: dealing with a developing teenager. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wader Study&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, 123(1): 1–3, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E. Rakhimberdiev&lt;/strong&gt;, A. Saveliev, T. Piersma, and J. Karagicheva. FLightR: An R package for reconstructing animal paths from solar geolocation loggers. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Methods in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D. W. Winkler, F. A. Gandoy, J. I. Areta, M. J. Iliff, &lt;strong&gt;E. Rakhimberdiev&lt;/strong&gt;, K. J. Kardynal, and K. A. Hobson. Long-distance range expansion and rapid adjustment of migration in a newly established population of barn swallows breeding in Argentina. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Current Biology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, (7): 1080–1084, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;S. Lisovski, H. Schmaljohann, E. S. Bridge, S. Bauer, A. Farnsworth, S. A. Gauthreaux, S. Hahn, M. T. Hallworth, C. M. Hewson, J. F. Kelly, F. Liechti, P. P. Marra, &lt;strong&gt;E. Rakhimberdiev&lt;/strong&gt;, J. D. Ross, N. E. Seavy, M. D. Sumner, C. M. Taylor, D. W. Winkler, S. J. Wotherspoon, and M. B. Wunder. Inherent limits of light-level geolocation may lead to over-interpretation. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Current Biology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, (28): R99–R100, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breeding ecology of tree swallows</title>
      <link>https://eldarrak.github.io/project/breeding_ecology_of_tree_swallows/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eldarrak.github.io/project/breeding_ecology_of_tree_swallows/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had a pleasure to work in Ithaca with David Winkler. He started and for many years maintains a huge colony of nest boxes. Tree swallows living in these boxes are cute birds with low survival rates and this makes them different  from shorebirds I used to work before. These birds just have to reproduce, so they arrive super early to get a nest box. Lay second clutch if the first was not successful and have to find food despite coldsnaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D. W. Winkler, M. K. Luo, and &lt;strong&gt;E. Rakhimberdiev&lt;/strong&gt;. Temperature effects on food supply and chick mortality in tree swallows (&lt;em&gt;Tachycineta bicolor&lt;/em&gt;). &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oecologia&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, (173): 129–138, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D. W. Winkler, K. M. Ringelman, P. O. Dunn, L. Whittingham, J. T. Hussell David, R. G. Clark, R. D. Dawson, J. L. Scott, A. Rose, S. H. Austin, R. W. Douglas, M. P. Lombardo, P. A. Thorpe, D. Shutler, R. J. Robertson, M. Stager, M. Leonard, A. G. Horn, J. Dickinson, V. Ferretti, V. Massoni, F. Bulit, J. C. Reboreda, M. Liljesthröm, M. Quiroga, &lt;strong&gt;E. Rakhimberdiev&lt;/strong&gt;, and D. R. Ardia. Latitudinal variation in clutch size–lay date regressions in tachycineta swallows: effects of food supply or demography? &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ecography&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, 37(7): 670–678, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J. Karagicheva, M. Liebers, &lt;strong&gt;E. Rakhimberdiev&lt;/strong&gt;, K. K. Hallinger, A. Saveliev, and D. W. Winkler. Differences in size between first and replacement clutches match the seasonal decline in single clutches in tree swallows tachycineta bicolor. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ibis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, 158(3): 607-613, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
