<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Software on </title>
    <link>https://eldarrak.github.io/tags/software/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Software on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Eldar Rakhimberdiev</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/software/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>FLightR: an R package for Solar Geolocation data Analysis</title>
      <link>https://eldarrak.github.io/project/solar_geolocation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eldarrak.github.io/project/solar_geolocation/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;While working at Cornell University with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eeb.cornell.edu/winkler/wordpress&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;David Winkler&lt;/a&gt; in 2011 I started development of a new technique for solar geolocation data analysis. Solar geolocators are the tiniest devices one can put on animals that record only light levels over time. In 2012 I joined a project &amp;lsquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nceas.ucsb.edu/featured/bridge&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Establishing an Open-source Animal-tracking Analysis Platform for Archival Geolocators&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; supported by the National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end I have developed R package &lt;strong&gt;FLightR&lt;/strong&gt;. I hope it will help researchers to get year round estimates of migratory animals locations and behavioural states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how &lt;strong&gt;FLightR&lt;/strong&gt; works:
&lt;img src=&#34;https://eldarrak.github.io/img/geolocation_move_ecol.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;geolocation&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NB&lt;/strong&gt;: Please, do not ask FLightR and other geolocation related questions over email, go with them to &lt;a href=&#34;http://ornithologyexchange.org/forums/forum/259-geolocator-discussion-support/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;ornithologyexchange&lt;/a&gt; and with package problems to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/eldarrak/FLightR/issues&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;dedicated GitHub page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;publications&#34;&gt;Publications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E. Rakhimberdiev&lt;/strong&gt;, D. W. Winkler, E. Bridge, N. E. Seavy, D. Sheldon, T. Piersma, and A. Saveliev. A hidden markov model for reconstructing animal paths from solar geolocation loggers using templates for light intensity. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Movement Ecology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, 3(1), 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E. Rakhimberdiev&lt;/strong&gt;, N. Senner, M. Verhoeven, D. Winkler, W. Bouten, and T. Piersma. Comparing inferences of solar geolocation data against high-precision gps data: annual movements of a double-tagged black-tailed godwit. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Journal of Avian Biology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, 47(4): 589-596, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E. Rakhimberdiev&lt;/strong&gt;. Ornithology by light levels today: dealing with a developing teenager. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wader Study&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, 123(1): 1–3, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E. Rakhimberdiev&lt;/strong&gt;, A. Saveliev, T. Piersma, and J. Karagicheva. FLightR: An R package for reconstructing animal paths from solar geolocation loggers. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Methods in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;D. W. Winkler, F. A. Gandoy, J. I. Areta, M. J. Iliff, &lt;strong&gt;E. Rakhimberdiev&lt;/strong&gt;, K. J. Kardynal, and K. A. Hobson. Long-distance range expansion and rapid adjustment of migration in a newly established population of barn swallows breeding in Argentina. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Current Biology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, (7): 1080–1084, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
