<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Movement_ecology on </title>
    <link>https://eldarrak.github.io/tags/movement_ecology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Movement_ecology on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2020 Eldar Rakhimberdiev</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://eldarrak.github.io/tags/movement_ecology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Flyway ecology: full annual cycle ecology of long-distance migrants</title>
      <link>https://eldarrak.github.io/project/population_ecology_of_long_distant_migrants/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eldarrak.github.io/project/population_ecology_of_long_distant_migrants/</guid>
      <description>Where and how populations of seasonal migrants are limited? How parts of the annual cycle are interconnected? How migrants adjust to the ongoing changes?  To a great surprise we still have very limited answer to this questions. My current understanding is that there is not default limiting time or place and migratory populations respond to the selection pressures by adjusting their distributions in time and space. Together with Theunis Piersma, my teacher in Flyway Ecology, and his team we have already obtained some interesting results:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FLightR: an R package for Solar Geolocation data Analysis</title>
      <link>https://eldarrak.github.io/project/solar_geolocation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eldarrak.github.io/project/solar_geolocation/</guid>
      <description>While working at Cornell University with David Winkler in 2011 I started development of a new technique for solar geolocation data analysis. Solar geolocators are the tiniest devices one can put on animals that record only light levels over time. In 2012 I joined a project &amp;lsquo;Establishing an Open-source Animal-tracking Analysis Platform for Archival Geolocators&amp;rsquo; supported by the National Center for Ecological Analysis and Synthesis.
In the end I have developed R package FLightR.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>